A Guide to the Alice Langley Hsieh Papers, 1943-1978
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- Series III: Subject Files, 1950-1978.
  - Cultural Revolution.
    - File of newspaper clippings, 4/68-6/68. (Box 6)
    - L. Crampton, rought draft of "Where the CR Is Heading," (Filed with ALH Correspondence), 9/68. (Box 1)
    - RAND Memo RM-5934-PR M. Gurton, "The Foreign Ministry and Foreign Affairs in China's Cultural Revolution," (Filed with RAND Documents), 3/69. (Box 7)
    - RAND Document, T. W. Robinson, "Chou En Lai's Role in China's Cultural Revolution," (Filed with RAND Documents), 3/31/69. (Box 7)
    - E. Joffe, "The Chinese Army on the Eve of the Cultural Revolution: Prelude to Intervention," 8/69. (Box 6)
    - Wen Shun Chi, "The GPCR in Idealogical Perspective," in Asian Survey, 8/69. (Box 6)
    - U. of Calif. CCS reprint, "Two Chinese Revolutions: The GPCR in Idealogical Perspective," 9/69. (Box 6)
    - Parris Chang, "The Role of Ch'en Po-Ta in the CR," (Filed with ALH Correspondence), 11/12/69. (Box 1)
    - RAND Memo, "Chinese Communist Revolutionary Strategy and the Land Problem," (Filed with RAND Documents), 4/70. (Box 7)
    - H. Harding, "Modernization and Mao: The Logic of the CR in the 70's," 8/70. (Box 6)
    - Ellis Joffe, "The Chinese Army and the Cultural Revolution: The Politics of Intervention," in Current Scene, 12/7/70. (Box 6)
    - G. Bennett, "Military Regions and Provincial Party Secretaries: One Outcome of China's Cultural Revolution," 12/28/72. (Box 6)
    - Ellis Joffe, "The Chinese Army after the CR: The Effects of Intervention," in China Quarterly, 7-9/73. (Box 1)
  - Davydov, Boris. (Box 3)
    - Memos of ALH conversations, (Filed with ALH Papers), 1969.
  - East-West Relations. (Box 6)
    - Adelphi Paper #147, "Defense Budgeting--British and American."
    - R. A. Scalapino, "Reflections on East-West Relations," in Survey, no. 3/4 (100/101), Summer/Fall 1976.
    - Adelphi Paper #139, "Sea Power and Western Security."
  - Foreign Broadcast Information Service. (Box 6)
    - Daily Reports for 3/57, 6/57, and 11/58.
  - Institute for Defense Analysis (IDA) Documents.
    - IDA Research Paper P-429, H. C. Hinton, "Policy Making and the Power Struggle in CC During the Cultural Revolution," 2/68. (Box 6)
    - Task order (From Asst. Secy. of Defense) To IDA, re decision making in the Chinese high command, 1/19/70. (Box 6)
    - Internal note, "China's Nuclear Strategy and a U. S. Anti-China ABM," N-711R, (Filed with ALH Publications), 4/9/70. (Box 4)
    - A. L. Hsieh, "Communist China's Evolving Military Strategy and Doctrine," (Filed with ALH Publications), 6/70. (Box 4)
    - Paper P-1335 Nathan N. White, "Future U.S. Policy Toward Korea: Analysis, Alternatives, and Recommendations," 3/78. (Box 6)
  - Jackson, Henry L. (Box 3)
    - Position papers on that in U.S.-China relations, (Filed with ALH Papers), 1967-1968.
  - Japan, Armament Strategy.
    - Nakasone interview, (Filed with ALH Papers), 1/20/70. (Box 3)
    - A. L. Hsieh ms on Japan defense policy, (Filed with ALH Manuscripts), c.1970. (Box 2)
    - A. L. Hsieh draft, "Primary Projections of Japan's Security Policy," (Filed with ALH Manuscripts), c.1971. (Box 2)
  - Japan-China Relations.
    - A. L. Hsieh drafts and correspondence on strategy and tactics of CC's foreign policy toward Japan, (Filed with ALH Correspondence). (Box 1)
    - Draft of book contents, Dr. Nathan N. White, People's Diplomacy: An Analysis of its Use by China in Influence Japan, 1949-1976, c.1977. (Box 6)
  - Japan, Nuclear.
    - V. Gilinsky and P. Langer, RAND memo RM-5366-PR, "The Japanese Civilian Nuclear Program," (Filed with RAND Documents), 8/67. (Box 7)
    - V. Gilinsky, RAND memo RM-5998-PR/ISA, "The Possibility of Uranium Enrichment in Japan," (Filed with RAND Documents), 6/69. (Box 7)
    - M. Plesset, "Nuclear Developments in Japan," 9/69. (Box 6)
  - Japan, Socialist Party in. (Box 6)
    - Untitled ms, 189 pp, re Japanese Socialism, c.1970.
  - Japanese Language Documents. (Box 6)
    - Two copies of newspaper Ajicho Geppo, 11/71.
  - KTTH (Kung Tso T'ung Hsien).
    - Index of Contents. (Box 9)
    - Photostats of orignials in Chinese, nos. 1-30, (Filed with Chinese Language, Documents in), 11/1/61-8/26/61. (Box 6)
  - Lin Piao.
    - Research Analysis Corp. Paper, "Increased Influence of Lin Piao and the Armed Forces," 3/6/68. (Box 6)
    - C. J. V. Murphy, "Who Killed Lin Piao?" in National Review, 6/8/73. (Box 6)
    - D. N. Rowe, "The End of Lin Piao: Another View," in National Review, 8/3/73. (Box 6)
    - Chinese text and translation, "Changes of CC Military Cadres Since Lin Piao as Defense Minister." (Box 6)
    - R. Liang, "The Current and Past of Lin Piao," (Filed with RAND Documents), 8/22/67. (Box 7)
  - Mao Tse Tung.
    - H. A. Steiner, Maoism: A Sourcebook, 1952. (Box 7)
    - Mao interviewed by Edgar Snow, (Filed with ALH Correspondence), Spring 1965. (Box 1)
    - R. Mac Farquhar, "Mao's Last Revolution," in Foreign Affairs, 10/66. (Box 7)
    - Special Study #13, "Mao Tse Tung and the Cultural Revolution," 5/67. (Box 7)
    - Mao Speech, "Strategic Development in the Cultural Revolution," 3/68. (Box 7)
    - L. Crampton, "Mao's Perception of the Military," 1/24/69. (Box 7)
    - Sayings of Mao, in China News Analysis, no. 631, (Filed in China News Analysis). (Box 5)
    - R. Scalapino, "The Struggle for Mao and the Future," in Orbis, Spring 1977. (Box 7)
    - J. K. Fairbank, "The State That Mao Built." (Box 7)
    - C. K. Hsieh, handwritten chapters of Mao and the Chinese Red Army, (Filed with CKH Papers). (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Documents. (Box 7)
    - Photocopies, "Maritime Defense Forces," 1959.
    - Loose page 45 of a roster of CC political and military officials.
    - Page 824 of unidentified mss.
  - Miscellaneous Journal Articles. (Box 7)
    - Asian Survey, v. 7, no. 1 (1/67) and v. 3, no.7 (7/63); topics on CC and Far East.
    - A. Harelick, "The Cuban Missile Crisis," in World Politics, 4/64.
    - File of articles from Orbis, World Today, Asian Survey, etc., on a variety of topics, including William Mancester, "The Last Shogun."
  - Nakasone, Yosuhiro.
    - Lecture by, "Basic Understanding of the Problems Concerning the Constitution, Foreign Policy, and National Defense," 8/11/67. (Box 7)
    - A. L. Hsieh interview with, (Filed with ALH Papers), 1/20/70. (Box 3)
    - Memos of A. L. Hsieh conversations with Momoi and Saeki re forthcoming visit of, (Filed with ALH Papers), 8/21/70 and 8/28/70. (Box 3)
  - Nuclear Arms, General. (Box 7)
    - M. Halperin papers on Nuclear Test Ban and Deterrent Capacity, 4/63.
    - C. Jonsson, "The Soviet Union and the Test Ban: Inta-Bloc and Internal Bargaining," c.1972.
    - Adelphi Papers #112 and #113, "Prospects for Nuclear Proliferation," 1975.
    - Adelphi Paper #140, "The Future of Land-Based Missile Forces," Winter 1977.
    - C. S. Gray, "The Geopolitics of the Nuclear Era: Heartland, Rimland, and The Technology Revolution," 1977.
  - Photographs and Posters. (Box 7)
    - Packet of photographs identifying certain Chinese officials.
    - Photograph of first Chinese nuclear explosion and a number of Maoist propaganda posters.
  - RAND Documents.
    - A. L. Hsieh, P-1894, "Communist China and Nuclear Warfare," (Filed with ALH Publications), 2/60. (Box 3)
    - ALH, P-2022, "The Chinese Genie: Peking's Role in the Nuclear Test-Ban Negotiations," (Filed with ALH Publications), 6/20/60. (Box 3)
    - ALH P-2719, "Communist China and the Nuclear Force," (Filed with ALH Publications), 3/63 and revised 8/63. (Box 3)
    - RM-3519-PR, "The Economy of the Chinese Mainland: National Income and Economic Development, 1953-59," vol. I and II, 4/63. (Box 7)
    - RM-3787-PR, O. Hoeffding, "Sino-Soviet Economic Relations, 1958-62," 8/63. (Box 7)
    - D-11724-PR, C. W. Chang, "Marshal Yeh Chien Ying on the Training of the PLA of CC," 9/18/63. (Box 7)
    - RM-11727-PR, C. W. Chang, "The 3rd and 4th Machine Building Ministries of Communist China," (in an envelope from "Carl Chang, Photographer"), 9/26/63. (Box 7)
    - RM-3825-RC, Feng Hwa Mah, "CC's Foreign Trade: Price Structure and Behavior," 10/63. (Box 7)
    - ALH, RM-3833-PR Abridged, "CC's Military Doctrine and Strategy," 1st adn 2nd printings, (Filed with ALH Publications), 10/63. (Box 3)
    - R. Scalapino, "Chou En Lai in Africa: A Talk with Questions and Answers," 3/20/64. (Box 7)
    - RM-4666-PR, update of "Civil Aviation in Communist China," originially published 6/66, c.1968. (Box 7)
    - ALH, "Upheaval in China and Implications for the Future," (Filed with ALH Publications),11/8/66 and 12/20/66. (Box 3)
    - ALH, "Presentation on the 'Great Proletarian Cultural Revulition' in China by Roderick MacFarquhar," (Filed with ALH Publications), 2/10/67. (Box 3)
    - R. Liang, "The Current and Past of Lin Piao," 8/22/67. (Box 7)
    - RM-5366-PR, V. Gilinsky and P. Langer, "The Japanese Civilian Nuclear Program," 8/67. (Box 7)
    - ALH, "Military Confrontation in Asia: The Chinese Viewpoint," (Filed with ALH Publications), 8/23/68. (Box 4)
    - RM-5934-PR, M. Gurton, "The Foreign Ministry and Foreign Affairs in CC's Cultural Revolution," 3-69. (Box 7)
    - T. W. Robinson, "Chou En Lai's Role in China's Cultural Revolution," 3/31/69. (Box 7)
    - RM-5662-PR/ISA, "China's Industrial Growth--Investment Outlays, 1952-1967," 5/69. (Box 7)
    - RM-5841-PR/ISA, "China's Industrial Growth--Overall Level of Investment and its Relation to General Growth Rate," 5/69. (Box 7)
    - RM-5625-PR/ISA, "Chinese Industrial Growth," 5/69. (Box 7)
    - RM-5998-PR/ISA, V. Gilinsky, "The Possibility of Uranium Enrichment in Japan," 6/69. (Box 7)
    - T. W. Robinson, "Border Negotiations and the Future of Sino-Soviet Relations," 8/71. (Box 7)
  - RAND Personnel Rosters. (Box 7)
    - Rosters, 1969, 1974.
  - Red Guard. (Box 7)
    - Publications of, 1967.
  - Sino-Indian Relations. (Box 9)
    - File of reprints on the Border Dispute, 1966.
  - Sino-Soviet Relations.
    - File of reprints, including a one-page photostat from China Communist, acknowledging Stalin's error, but pledging continued advance of Communism "under the leadership of the Soviet Union," 4/5/56. (Box 9)
    - "Reported Agreements Between the USSR and China," through 6/21/56. (Box 9)
    - RAND Memo, "Sino-Soviet Economic Relations, 1958-62," (Filed with RAND Documents). (Box 7)
    - T. Wolfe, "The Soviet Union and the Sino-Soviet Border Dispute," 8/65. (Box 9)
    - MIT Center for International Studies Report C65-19, William Griffith, "Sino-Soviet Relations, 1964-65," 1965. (Box 9)
    - H. Hinton, outline of "The PLA and Sino-Soviet Relations," (Filed with ALH Correspondence), 4/8/68. (Box 1)
    - T. W. Robinson, "The Border Negotiations and the Future of Sino-Soviet Relations," (Filed with RAND Documents), 8/71. (Box 7)
    - G. Bennett, "The Quisling Hypothesis: Chinese Politics and Soviet Intervention," 5/3/74. (Box 9)
    - A. L. Hsieh, "The China-Russa Treaty of 1945, Compared," (Filed with ALH Manuscripts). (Box 2)
  - Snow, Edgar.
    - Service, John S., "Edgar Snow: Some Personal Reminiscences." (Box 9)
    - Snow interview with Mao Tse Tung, (Filed with ALH Correspondence), Spring 1965. (Box 1)
  - Tsien, H. S. (Box 9)
    - Typed biography, prepared by H. Boorman for Biographical Dictionary of Republican China, 10/68.
  - USSR. (Box 9)
    - Adelphi Papers #147 and #148, "Decision-Making in Soviet Weapon Procurement."
  - U.S.-China Relations.
    - R. Scalapino, Statement for Subcommittee on Asian and Pacific Affiars, "Sino-American Relations in an International Context." (Box 9)
    - Henry "Scoop" Jackson information given to ALH re Nixon Era thaw in relations, (Filed with ALH Papers). (Box 3)
    - Report of Wingspread Conference (Johnson Foundation), "Prospects for U.S.-China Relations," 5/74. (Box 9)
  - U.S.-Korea Relations.
    - A. L. Hsieh file on the Pueblo Incident, (Filed with ALH Papers), 1968-1969. (Box 1)
    - Nathan White, "Future U.S. Policy Toward Korea: Analysis, Alternatives, and Recommendations," (Filed with IDA Documents), 3/78. (Box 6)
  - Vietcong. (Box 9)
    - Objectives and strategies of, reprint from Ramparts, 11/72.
  - Vietnam War. (Box 3)
    - Role of China in, CBS News Panel Broadcast, (Filed with ALH Presentation).
  - Yang Yung. (Box 9)
    - Biographical file (notes by CKH).
  - Yeh Chen-Ying. (Box 9)
    - Biographical file (notes by CKH).